A Guide to the WRVA Radio Collection, 1925-2000
Library of Virginia
- Series XI: Sound Recordings, 1929-1995, 630 compact discs. Duration: 317 hr., 40 min., 38 sec.
  - Sideviews on the News: Christmas Eve, 1956-1957, (WRVA - 622-623); 2 compact discs. Duration: 21 min., 31 sec.
    Jack Clements hosts this edition of Sideviews on the News, in which he goes to the North Pole to investigate rumors that Santa Claus will be unable to deliver his toys due to the fact the Rudolph's red nose is not working. The supposed cause of the problem is the commercialization of Christmas, and the program is intended to remind people of the religious basis of the holiday. WRVA-622 is the 1956 broadcast of this story, and WRVA-623 is the same story but from 1957.
  - Sideviews on the News: Colonel Wright, New Chief of Police, 24 February 1961, (WRVA - 542); 1 compact disc. Duration: 5 min., 54 sec.
    Lon Backman hosts this episode of Sideviews on the News, in which he interviews John Wright, the new chief of police for the city of Richmond. Wright, who had been on the force forty-one years at the time of his appointment, joined the force at age 18 and served as acting chief for nearly a year. Backman asks him about his plans for the force, what the previous year as acting chief was like and the response of his wife to his new position.
  - Sideviews on the News: Dean Raymond B. Pinchbeck Tribute, 4 February 1957, (WRVA - 159); 1 compact disc. Duration: 12 min., 35 sec.
    This program is a tribute to Raymond B. Pinchbeck (1900-1957), Dean at the University of Richmond, professor of economics, and host of WRVA's Radio Scholarship Quiz, who died on 4 February 1957. Includes reminiscences of and tributes to Pinchbeck from Carl Stutz, Ray Kennedy, and Walter R. Bishop, all employees of WRVA Radio. Stutz reminiscences about his years as one of Pinchbeck's students at the University of Richmond. Kennedy shares his memories working with Pinchbeck on the Radio Scholarship Quiz Show. Bishop recounts Pinchbeck's civic achievements and public service. Also includes a news tribute and excerpts from Pinchbeck's talk on the national radio broadcast, "This I Believe."
  - Sideviews on the News: Egypt-Arab League, 13 February 1958, (WRVA - 537); 1 compact disc. Duration: 10 min., 14 sec.
    Jack Clements hosts a discussion with a former dean from the School of Commerce at Cairo University about the League of Arab States, also commonly known as the Arab League. His guest defines the organization and comments that this goodwill tour of the United States is an effort to win friends for Egypt. He talks about the importance of the unity of Arab states, while Clements asks him questions about the relationship between the communists and the Arab states, how the Egyptians feel about Americans, the issue of Israel and where Egypt would stand if there was a war between the United States and Russia. His guest comments on the instance following the Civil War in which approximately fifty Confederate officers from Virginia went to Egypt to help them build their army.
  - Sideviews on the News: Enterprise Special Merger Annexation, [1960], (WRVA - 368-368a); 2 compact discs. Duration: 1 hr., 36 sec.
    Hosted by Lon Backman, this show features four different programs devoted to the issue of annexation of Henrico County by the City of Richmond. The date of the programs are not known, but thought to be from 1960. Backman interviews various individuals involved in the annexation/consolidation controversy. Horace Edwards, Richmond City Manager, discusses the annexation ordinance process, various studies taking place, court procedures, annexation case questions, costs involved, referendum procedures, and statewide trends in annexation cases. A. Howe Todd, executive director of the Richmond Regional Planning Commission, talks about the work and composition of the Commission, the merger/annexation process, tax issues, differences between annexation and merger, and the work of the Public Administration Service (PAS). Richmond City Councilman J. Edward Lawler explains the issues involved, tax burden, business tax revenues in the city vs. county tax revenues, who would benefit from annexation, the chances of annexation succeeding, the resolution introduced by him on annexation, effect of the recent flood in Richmond on the issue, and race and school issues and their effect on the proposal. Joseph T. Williams, Jr., a member of the Virginia House of Delegates, states his position on the issue and why is vehemently opposed to annexation, discusses his legislative work in the General Assembly on the topic, and how issues of race could affect the question of annexation. Burl A. Parks, director of city planning, sums up the issues involved in annexation, merger, and status quo. Parks discusses what the alternatives are, forms of government, services provided, and tax issues involved in all three options.
  - Sideviews on the News: Hawaii Elections, 6 August 1959, (WRVA - 363); Duration: 5 min., 55 sec.
    1 compact disc. Lon Backman, WRVA news broadcaster, reports on the first free elections in Hawaii. Includes sound bytes of radio broadcasts concerning the elections from Station KGU-AM in Honolulu.
  - Sideviews on the News: Hungarian General, 18 February 1960, (WRVA - 510); 1 compact disc. Duration: 7 min., 24 sec.
    Hosted by Jack Clements, this show features an interview with Bela K. Kiraly, leader of the Hungarian resistance movement. Kiraly discusses the struggle by the resistance against the Soviet army in his country in 1956, and also the role of Radio Free Europe in combating Communism.
  - Sideviews on the News: Interview with C. T. Overstreet, 23 August 1962, (WRVA - 235); 1 compact disc. Duration: 12 min., 16 sec.
    Hosted by Joe Lowen, this show features an interview with Carson Thomas Overstreet (1901-2000) of Glen Allen, Virginia concerning the possible defection of his "foster" son James Joseph Dresnok to North Korea. Overstreet discusses Dresnock's childhood, divorce, prior military service, and what he has learned from the U.S. military concerning Dresnok's disappearance while serving in the Army in South Korea near the demilitarized zone.
  - Sideviews on the News: Juvenile Series, 15 November 1957, (WRVA - 535); 1 compact disc. Duration: 27 min., 9 sec.
    Jack Clements hosts this three part series of Sideviews on the News, which explores the issue of juvenile crime and delinquency in Richmond. The first part features a discussion of this "serious problem in Richmond" with Kermit V. Rocke, associate judge of the Richmond Juvenile and Domestic Relations Court. Clements asks Rocke his opinions on juvenile delinquency in Richmond as compared to other cities in the country and what he thinks the root causes are for the problem. Part two features an interview with the Reverend Paul Edward Crandall, executive secretary of the Richmond Baptist Association, on what the churches are doing to meet the problem of juvenile crime; and part three features three student guests from John Marshall High School, who also share their opinions and views on the causes and possible solutions to juvenile delinquency in the city.
  - Sideviews on the News: Leaves and Lives, 30 August 1965, (WRVA - 509); 1 compact disc. Duration: 5 min., 33 sec.
    This show features Ray Turner reading a poem entitled "Leaves and Lives," about a walk through Maymont Park in Richmond and how the seasons of the year relate to the seasons of one's life.
  - Sideviews on the News: Mental Discussions, 10-12 August 1959, (WRVA - 364); 1 compact disc. Duration: 44 min., 41 sec.
    Lon Backman and Jack Clements, WRVA news reporters, explore the issues and problems with the state mental hospitals in a series of five programs. Part 1 contains a discussion with a patient at Western State Hospital and with Dr. Howard H. Ashbury, clinical director of psychology at Western State Hospital, regarding the patient's prognosis. Part 2 contains an interview with Dr. James B. Pettis, superintendent of Western State Hospital, who recounts the history of Western State Hospital and the state of affairs in Virginia's mental hospitals. Also includes an interview with one of the hospital's elderly patients. Part 3 includes a discussion with Dr. Howard H. Ashbury concerning overcrowding. Part 4 contains a discussion with John Edward Raine, chairman of a special legislative commission studying the problems of the aged in Virginia's mental hospitals. Part 5 contains an interview with State Senator Edward Willey, chairman of the Virginia State Hospital Board.
  - Sideviews on the News: Mr. O'Neal Prevention of Blindness, (WRVA - 577); 1 compact disc. Duration: 11 min., 8 sec.
    Lon Backman hosts this episode of Sideviews on the News, in which he interviews James E. O'Neal, the director of Industrial Service for the National Society for the Prevention of Blindness. The focus of the interview is the use of industrial safety spectacles with shatter resistant lenses as safer for people than wearing regular glasses when playing sports, doing industrial jobs, fishing, hunting or mowing the lawn. O'Neal also talks specifically about the work of the Industrial Service section of the society and the importance of eye protection to prevent or eliminate unnecessary eye damage. The date of this program is unknown.
  - Sideviews on the News: Police Series, 1956-1957, (WRVA - 170-174); 5 compacts discs. Duration: 2 hrs., 49 min., 51 sec.
    Covering the period 4 October 1956 through 4 April 1957 and hosted by Jack Clements. This program includes fifteen parts in the series detailing the duties and responsibilities of the Richmond Police Department. Included are shows discussing the Juvenile, Records and Communications, and Traffic Safety Divisions, interviews with police officers while on patrol, coverage of the booking of a suspect and the various procedures that are followed, coverage of a vice-squad raid, discussions on safecrackers, pick-pockets, shoplifters, and automobile thieves, a demonstration of a speed radar, on-the-scene reports of routine traffic stops, as well as a tour of the Richmond Police Academy which includes a discussion on the training of new officers, and the future outlook for the police profession.
  - Sideviews on the News: Robert E. Lee's Birthday, 18 January 1957, (WRVA - 143); 1 compact disc. Duration: 10 min., 23 sec.
    This program is recorded in the Virginia Room of the White House of the Confederacy on the occasion of Robert E. Lee's birthday. Walter Bishop, WRVA public relations director, and Jack Clements, WRVA news editor, interview India Thomas, house regent of the Museum of the Confederacy. She discusses the life of Robert E. Lee and the various artifacts of Lee the museum owns. Also includes a speech of Governor Thomas B. Stanley during which he praises Lee and his effort to preserve states' rights.
  - Sideviews on the News: Robert Heberle, 11 May 1960, (WRVA - 565); 1 compact disc. Duration: 7 min., 55 sec.
    Hosted by Lon Backman, this show featured Robert J. Heberle (1907-1975), a lawyer and member of Richmond City Council. Heberle discusses his background, outside interests, career, and his interest in the oversight of Richmond's city budget and real estate tax issues.
  - Sideviews on the News: Rock and Roll, 17 March 1958, (WRVA - 451); 1 compact disc. Duration: 9 min., 40 sec.
    In this episode of the regular WRVA program, Sideviews on the News, Jack Clements interviews Richmond city police Sergeant Robert Milliken from the Juvenile and Missing Persons Division. The topic is Rock and Roll, "the new music." The discussion revolves around live rock and roll shows and their influence on juvenile delinquency. While the officer concedes that an incident involving six juveniles from the prior evening was not caused by a show at the Mosque, he does say that often the music does incite the youngsters to "get uncontrollable and go into a frenzied state."
  - Sideviews on the News: Sales Tax, Senator Byrd, 28 January 1960, (WRVA - 540); 1 compact disc. Duration: 10 min., 48 sec.
    Lon Backman hosts this segment of Sideviews on the News, in which Senator Harry F. Byrd, Jr., reacts to Governor Almond's comment that his proposed state budget is "bare bones." Byrd discusses the 33.8 percent proposed increase in state expenditures and the 3 percent sales tax bill Almond recommends. Also covered is the possible budget surplus, which at the time had the potential of being the second highest in Virginia history.
  - Sideviews on the News: Senator A. Willis Robertson, 25-27 October 1961, (WRVA - 541); 1 compact disc. Duration: 29 min., 13 sec.
    This is a recording of a three-part Sideviews on the News program featuring United States Senator A. Willis Robertson of Virginia. Robertson provides a viewpoint on the "political philosophies, moral philosophies and an assessment of the physical realities in our world today." This includes his feelings about serving as a United States Senator, the United Nations and the United States' responsibility to that body, the attitudes of Americans in the tense times of fears about communism, and states' rights. Hosted by Harry Monroe. This recording is the broadcast version. The original interview between Harry Monroe and Senator Robertson is on WRVA - 230.
  - Sideviews on the News: Senator Robertson and Hank [Harry] Monroe Original Interview, 27 October 1961, (WRVA - 230); 1 compact disc. Duration: 24 min., 15 sec.
    Harry (Hank) Monroe, WRVA broadcaster, interviews United States Senator A. Willis Robertson (1887-1971) of Virginia. Robertson reminisces about his tenure in the Virginia state legislature, and talks about his current workload in the U.S. Senate, federal government interference and bureaucracy, military appropriations, U.S.-Soviet relations and the Cold War, the federal deficit, inflation, the Berlin crisis, the United Nations, and the faith of the citizens of the United States in their country. This recording is the original interview conducted. For the broadcast version see WRVA - 541.
  - Sideviews on the News: Special Turnpike Ceremonies, 30 June 1958, (WRVA - 312); 1 compact disc. Duration: 17 min., 35 sec.
    This compact disc contains a special episode of Sideviews on the News, covering the ceremonies held in celebration of the opening of the Richmond-Petersburg Turnpike on 30 June 1958. This is an edited version of the full-length recordings contained on WRVA -311. Jack Clements is the host. Speakers at the ceremonies include T. Coleman Andrews, president of the Richmond Chamber of Commerce, who talks about the safety features of this "dream of modern transportation"; F. Henry Garber, mayor of Richmond, who discusses the turnpike's impact on retail and civic relations between Richmond, Petersburg, Hopewell and other communities; former Governor Thomas Stanley; and Governor J. Lindsay Almond.
  - Sideviews on the News: Steel Strike, 16 July 1959, (WRVA - 359); Duration: 8 min., 57 sec.
    1 compact disc. Lon Backman, WRVA news reporter, examines the nationwide steel strike and its potential impact on Richmond and Virginia.
  - Sideviews on the News - Tredegar Iron Works, 30 April - 2 May 1957, (WRVA - 175); Duration: 40 min., 11 sec.
    Hosted by Jack Clements, this program includes three segments on the Tredegar Iron Works in Richmond, Virginia. The shows were recorded live at the Tredegar company site, and include a tour of the facilities, history of the company, information on the types of products produced and methods employed, and the future of the company. Interviews are conducted with Edward H. Trigg (1893-1975), vice-president of Tredegar, and Christian E. Grosser (1909-1983), chief engineer at Philip Morris.
  - Sideviews on the News: Tribute to Robert E. Lee, 21 January 1958, (WRVA - 358); 1 compact disc. Duration: 9 min., 55 sec.
    Recording of a eulogy of Robert E. Lee delivered on the floor of the Virginia House of Delegates by Delegate E. Ralph James of Hampton. Also includes Jack Clements, WRVA news editor and host of Sideviews on the News, discussing the first American victory in the War of 1812 at the site of present day Talladega, Alabama.
  - Sideviews on the News: Valentine's Day; Capitol Hotel Fire, 14 February 1958, (WRVA - 445); 1 compact disc. Duration: 14 min., 12 sec.
    This edition of Sideviews on the News is the Valentine's Day special, featuring a discussion of the historical writings pertaining to love and the holiday. Jack Clements is the host. Included are quotes from the likes of Cicero, Napoleon, John Keats, Robert and Elizabeth Barrett Browning, and Victor Hugo. Also included are other historical tidbits and facts about the holiday. This part of the recording is approximately 9 minutes. The second part of the recording is dedicated to two minutes of news coverage of a fire at the Capitol Hotel, near Grace Street between 8th and 9th streets.
  - Sideviews on the News: Veterans Day, 11 November 1958, (WRVA - 450); 1 compact disc. Duration: 9 min., 52 sec.
    Frank Wilson hosts this episode of Sideviews on the News. The report provides a historic overview of the anniversary of the armistice of 1918. Includes clips of President Franklin Delano Roosevelt speaking on the holiday in 1941, as well as Dwight D. Eisenhower speaking at a ceremony honoring the unknown dead from World War II and the Korean War in the spring of 1958.
  - Sideviews on the News: Virginia General Assembly Public Hearings on School Legislation, 5-6 Sept. 1956, (WRVA - 141); 1 compact disc. Duration: 27 min., 58 sec.
    This program covers the Virginia General Assembly's public hearings on school legislation. Includes excerpts of statements from people with various views on how Virginia should handle the desegregation issue. The first track contains statements of Delegate J. Randolph Tucker of Richmond, and former Governor Colgate W. Darden supporting the Gray Plan. The second track includes statements from Hal Boyd, president of the Virginia AFL-CIO, opposing the Stanley Plan, Adele Clark calling for some degree of compliance with the Supreme Court decision, Joseph Freehill, Fairfax County Board of Supervisors, explaining that desegregation policy should be set at the state level, Lester Banks, president of the Virginia NAACP, calling for integration at all deliberate speed, and State Senator Edward O. McCue, Jr., of Charlottesville, outlining his plan for handling the segregation issue. The third track includes the statement of J. Segar Gravatt, taking exception to Darden's remark of the day earlier and stating that a course of moderation on the issue is unacceptable.
  - Sideviews on the News: Whiskey by the Drink, 27 January 1960, (WRVA - 539); 1 compact disc. Duration: 10 min., 22 sec.
    Lon Backman hosts this recording of Sideviews on the News. The topic of discussion is a bill introduced into the House of Delegates calling for a local option referendum on serving whiskey and other spirits by the drink. Norfolk delegates Calvin Childress and Henry Howell, the patrons of the bill, are Backman's guests. The basis of the bill was the creation of a new type of liquor license to be administered by the Alcoholic Beverage Control Board to regulate hotels and restaurants serving spirits by the drink. There was a concern that without the passage of this bill, the Tidewater area would suffer due to competition with other Atlantic seaboard resorts unencumbered by laws preventing such sales. Childress and Howell state that this bill would benefit Virginia tourism statewide and would put the decision making on whether to allow such sales in the hands of the people of each locality, rather than the General Assembly. The opposition from some religious groups is also discussed.
  - Silver Documentary, 1 November 1950, (WRVA - 351); 1 compact disc. Duration: 31 min., 47 sec.
    Recording of another program in a series of programs celebrating WRVA's 25th anniversary. Narrated by George Passage and Carl Stutz. Passage and Stutz recount the history of WRVA from its inaugural broadcast in 1925 to 1950 in the context of historical events, including the Depression, the rise of Hitler, King Edward VIII and Wallis Simpson, the Joe Louis-Max Schmeling fight, the Munich Peace Conference, Pearl Harbor, World War II, the dropping of the atomic bomb, and the 1948 Presidential election. Includes sound bytes of various events and personalities.
  - Silver Star Quartet, 11 June 1947, (WRVA - 63); 1 compact disc. Duration: 15 min., 30 sec.
    This installment of the weekly gospel program includes a performance by the Silver Star Quartet's special guests, the Hopewell Jubilee Singers. Songs performed include "When Days are Dark and Friends are Few", "One Day" as performed by the Hopewell Jubilee Singers and "Oh, Lord, when my work on earth is done, I won't duress." Wesley Harvey is the narrator of the program.
  - Silver Star Quartet, (WRVA - 75); 1 compact disc. Duration: 6 min.
    Undated recording of clips of opening and closing segments for the program and background harmonizing by the Silver Star Quartet, which was formed in Richmond, Virginia, in 1932. Originally known as the Gospel Spirituals, the group's performances were first broadcast over the WRVA airwaves in 1939, the weekly program was most often presented at 6:30 a.m. each Sunday morning for over 61 years and had about 20 different members over the years. The last program was broadcast on 8 October 2000.
  - Silver Stars Open and Close, (WRVA - 76); 1 compact disc. Duration: 8 min., 6 sec.
    Undated sound clips of opening and closing segments for the program and background harmonizing by the Silver Star Quartet, which was formed in Richmond, Virginia, in 1932. Originally known as the Gospel Spirituals, the group's performances were first broadcast over the WRVA airwaves in 1939, the weekly program was most often presented at 6:30 a.m. each Sunday morning for over 61 years and had about 20 different members over the years. The last program was broadcast on 8 October 2000.
  - Silver Wedding Anniversary, 27 October 1950, (WRVA - 352); 1 compact disc. Duration: 31 min., 57 sec.
    Recording of an anniversary party for twenty-five couples married in 1925. This program is one of a series of programs celebrating WRVA's 25th anniversary. Hosted by George Passage and Lee Lively. Contains interviews with some of the couples, asking such questions as how they met, when and where they got engaged, and what does she cook for him? Each couple is asked how many business firms were established in 1925, with the winner receiving a second honeymoon at the Cavalier Hotel in Virginia Beach.
  - Song Hits of 1925, 27 October 1950, (WRVA - 345); 1 compact disc. Duration: 32 min., 23 sec.
    Contains music and a look back at early radios and notable events of 1925. Hosted by Carl Stutz and Marc Rogers. Broadcast in celebration of WRVA's 25th anniversary.
  - Songs of the Southlanders: WRVA 29th Birthday Special, 31 October 1954, (WRVA - 196); 1 compact disc. Duration: 30 min., 33 sec.
    Features inspirational music and religious gospel selections. The group's leader talks about their beginnings on WRVA and their upcoming schedule of appearances. Also included on the program is Joseph Matthews and the Sabbath Glee Club from the Fifth Street Baptist Church in Richmond. Walter Bishop interviews Matthews about the group's start on the station, and they perform a rendition of "Swing Low Sweet Chariot."
  - Southwest Virginia Flood Coverage, 7 April 1963, (WRVA - 416); 1 compact disc. Duration: 19 min., 2 sec.